<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a dissenter from his friend at the Hague concerning the penal laws and the test, shewing that the popular plea for liberty of conscience is not concerned in that question.</title>
            <author>Friend at the Hague.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25887</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12426005</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199742</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264214572</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12426005</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a dissenter from his friend at the Hague concerning the penal laws and the test, shewing that the popular plea for liberty of conscience is not concerned in that question.</title>
                  <author>Friend at the Hague.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Gedrunckt door Hans Verdraeght,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Tot de Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  Political aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:199742:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199742:1"/>
            <head>A Letter to a <hi>Dissenter</hi> from his Friend at the HAGUE, Concerning the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and the <hi>Test;</hi> shevving that the Popular Plea for <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> is not concerned in that Question.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Suppose you are very busie about the Choice of <hi>Parliament-Men,</hi> and all hands are at work to Elect such Members as may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the great Design to Repeal the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and the <hi>Test.</hi> The <hi>pretence</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess is very plausible; for all Men are fond of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience,</hi> vvho dissent from the Estab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished Religion; but you and I have liv'd long enough in the World to observe that the most <hi>pernicious Designs</hi> have been carried on, under the most <hi>plausible Pretences;</hi> and that is Reason enough to enquire vvhether there be no danger of it novv. I shall not say one vvord against <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> nor for <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests:</hi> Imagine the best things you possibly can of the one, and declame as much as you please against the other. For I do not see that <hi>either</hi> of them are concerned in the <hi>present Dispute;</hi> but only made use of to <hi>wheadle</hi> unthinking people, and to <hi>catch</hi> them with a very inviting <hi>Bait:</hi> and therefore before You engage too warmly in this Cause, I would offer some few things to your <hi>calm</hi> and <hi>deliberate</hi> Thoughts.</p>
            <p>The great Pretence is <hi>Liberty of Conscience;</hi> and if this were the <hi>true</hi> state of the Case, the Dispute would be more doubtful and perplexed: for that is an Argument a Man may talk of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, and it is not to be expected that Men who feel the <hi>want</hi> of Liberty, or taste the <hi>sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of it, should be persuaded by any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to forgo it when it may be had. But now, if Liberty of Conscience may be had without the Repeal of the Test and Penal Laws; if it be apparent to Men who will open their eyes, that the <hi>true spring</hi> of all this zeal for Repealing the Test and Penal Laws is <hi>not</hi> Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; if there be great <hi>danger</hi> that by consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Repeal, vve shall <hi>forfeit</hi> both the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of our Consciences</hi> and our <hi>Civil Liberties</hi> into the Bargain; then I presume You will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily grant that <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> as good a thing as it is, is <hi>no Reason</hi> for such a <hi>Repeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. As for the first, it is a very plain case; For you enjoy Liberty of Conscience <hi>Now,</hi> and yet the Penal Laws and Test <hi>are not Repealed.</hi> What <hi>greater Liberty</hi> do you desire than you now have? What can the <hi>Repeal</hi> of the Penal Laws and Test do for you which the Kings <hi>Declaration</hi> hath not done? You have his repeated <hi>Promises,</hi> his avow'd <hi>Principle</hi> that <hi>Conscience is not to be forc'd;</hi> and that no man ought to suffer <hi>meerly</hi> for his Religion; though the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> are not <hi>repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> yet they are <hi>suspended;</hi> they are not executed either against <hi>Papists</hi> or <hi>Dissenters,</hi> and you have the security of the Kings <hi>Declaration</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>If you say, that the King can quickly <hi>recall</hi> his Declaration, and <hi>reinforce</hi> the Penal Laws, if he find you <hi>obstinate</hi> against Repealing them; I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer first, It is very <hi>dishonorable</hi> to imagine such a thing of the King, after such a Declaration as <hi>this,</hi> vvhich he hath repeated the second time with all possible assurances of his Resolutions to stand to it: and that not as a meer Act of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> but as his own avowed <hi>Principle,</hi> that <hi>Conscience ought not to be forced.</hi> If you Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that the King may very <hi>Honourably recal</hi> this <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> vvhen you will <hi>not have</hi> it, but resolve to <hi>keep</hi> these persecuting Laws; I answer, Not, if it be against the <hi>Principles</hi> of his own <hi>Conscience</hi> to Persecute. Meer <hi>favours</hi> may be withdrawn when they are slighted; bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no man will violate his own <hi>Conscience,</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of such ingratitude. And yet this is not the case: You do not <hi>slight</hi> the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favor</hi> of his Declaration, but gladly <hi>accept</hi> the <hi>Liberty</hi> he gives; and all the World sees that You <hi>use</hi> it too: but instead of Repealing these Penal Laws, You chuse to rely upon his <hi>Royal Word</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensing Power;</hi> vvhich argues so great a <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> in him, and attributes such <hi>Authority</hi> to him, that it cannot possibly displease him. This is a plain sign, that you think your selves <hi>secure</hi> in his Reign; and can you think the King will persecute you in his <hi>own</hi> Reign, because you are contented to trust his <hi>Successors</hi> too? which would be a very <hi>odd</hi> kind of passion for <hi>Liberty of Conscience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To imagine the King should <hi>reinforce</hi> the Penal Laws upon your <hi>refusal</hi> to Repeal them, is to suspect that this great Zeal is not for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> but for the <hi>Repeal</hi> of the Penal Laws and Test; that is, that <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> is granted for the sake of Repealing the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests,</hi> not the Repeal of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests,</hi> desired for the sake of <hi>Liberty of Conscience;</hi> and then who knows what will become of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience, when the Penal Laws and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199742:2"/> Test are Repealed? If you suspect any such thing which never ought to be suspected of so <hi>just</hi> and <hi>indulgent</hi> a Prince, it is better to make the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment <hi>before,</hi> than <hi>after</hi> such a Repeal.</p>
            <p>Suppose the King should <hi>withdraw</hi> his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration upon Your refusal to comply. Who would put the Laws in Execution against you? They must either be <hi>Dissenters</hi> or <hi>Papists</hi> or the <hi>Church of England:</hi> I presume you do not fear that you should execute the Laws against <hi>Your selves;</hi> and as for <hi>Papists</hi> it vvere vvorth trying vvhether they vvho are so obnoxious to the Laws themselves, would put them in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution against <hi>Dissenters,</hi> especially after all their Clamors against them: and as for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> vvhen they have been so reproached by <hi>Papist<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for Executing these Laws already, though more at the instance of the Court than from their own inclination, they vvill no longer be made the instruments of such executions, only to serve the turn of them that vvill reproach them: So that if the <hi>Declaration</hi> vvere recalled, You have a moral certainty that the <hi>Penal Lavvs</hi> cannot be Executed in this Kings reign, because there is no body to execute them.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Test,</hi> You cannot pretend that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience is concern'd in the Repeal of <hi>that.</hi> You may go to <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and the <hi>Papists</hi> may go to <hi>Mass</hi> vvithout any disturbance though the <hi>Test</hi> be never repealed: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>only design</hi> of repealing that must be to give a legal Qualification to <hi>Papists</hi> to possess all places of <hi>Honour, Profit</hi> and <hi>Trust</hi> in the Nation; that is, to put your Lives and Liberties into <hi>their</hi> hands; which I confess is a great Complement to a Roman Catholick Prince; but a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may sometimes be <hi>overstrained.</hi> And yet it is such a Complement as they <hi>need not.</hi> For vve see they are qualified by the <hi>Dispensing Power,</hi> vvithout the <hi>Repeal</hi> of the <hi>Test;</hi> which hath made me often wonder vvhy they are so zealous to have it repealed. Do they still <hi>question</hi> the Kings <hi>Dispensing Power?</hi> And desire some <hi>better security?</hi> Let them say so then, and give up that point, and then vve'll talk with them about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing the <hi>Test:</hi> but there is no need of repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Law, since the King it seems hath <hi>power</hi> to dispense vvith it in his reign; and they are very sanguine men, if they hope to have any <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion</hi> for it in another! And if after all their boasts of a <hi>Dispensing Power,</hi> the Law still keeps them in avv, can it be the <hi>interest</hi> of <hi>Protestants</hi> to take off these restraints? Are they not <hi>insolent</hi> enough <hi>already,</hi> vvhile these threatning Lavvs hang over their heads? Or do vve hope that their <hi>modesty</hi> and <hi>good Nature</hi> vvill increase vvith their <hi>Povver?</hi> For my part I desire that all Men whom I fear may lie under a legal incapacity: for though their Force and Power may be the same, yet there is some difference, in point of <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Self-defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. There are many things which would make a wise man suspect that there is some <hi>farther De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign</hi> than <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> in all this zeal for repealing the Penal Laws and Test. For it would be very surprising to find a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Prince whose Conscience is directed by a <hi>Jesuit,</hi> to be really zealous for Liberty of Conscience; to see so many Popish pens imploy'd in pleading for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience, and declaiming against San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Laws, vvhen all the world knows vvhat Opinion the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> has about <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> what great friends the <hi>Jesuits</hi> are to it; how they abhor persecuting men for their Religion: vvitness the mild and gentle usage of the <hi>French Protestants</hi> by a King whose Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is directed by a tender hearted <hi>Jesuit.</hi> And if a Princes zeal for <hi>his Religion</hi> be much greater than for <hi>Liberty of Conscience;</hi> it would make one suspect that his chief design is to serve <hi>his Religion</hi> by it; and this is no nevv invention, but as old as the days of the Apostate <hi>Julian,</hi> when the same method was taken to reinforce <hi>Paganism</hi> by Liberty of Conscience. This was the last effort of <hi>dying Paganism;</hi> may it be so of <hi>Popery</hi> too.</p>
            <p>We know there was no talk of <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> till the Nobility and Gentry of the <hi>Church of England</hi> refused to take off the <hi>Test:</hi> and then there vvas no other vvay left, but to <hi>buy off</hi> the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Test</hi> with <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> which demonstrates that Liberty of Conscience is not the <hi>last End,</hi> but only a <hi>Means</hi> in order to some <hi>further End;</hi> and the <hi>Means</hi> is seldom va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued when the <hi>End</hi> is obtained. Men who can offer so much violence to their own <hi>Nature</hi> and the Principles of their <hi>Religion,</hi> as to <hi>grant</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience which of all things they <hi>hate,</hi> to procure a Repeal of the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> when that is done, can easily find some occasion to pretend a <hi>forfeiture</hi> of this <hi>Liberty,</hi> and to salve their Conscience and Honour together. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws</hi> to keep men from <hi>damning</hi> themselves will be thought more <hi>merciful</hi> than <hi>Liberty of Conscience;</hi> and the <hi>softness</hi> and <hi>tenderness</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, must give place to a <hi>Bigotry</hi> in Religion; and then vve shall <hi>in vain</hi> wish for our <hi>old Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Test</hi> again, when we feel the more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible smart of <hi>new ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though it be told us, that it hath <hi>always</hi> been his Majesties Persuasion that <hi>Conscience ought not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199742:2"/> to be forced,</hi> I think that is no <hi>security;</hi> because though this has alvvays been his <hi>Principle,</hi> yet it hath not always <hi>operated.</hi> VVe know whose hand was most concern'd both in <hi>making</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting</hi> Penal Laws in the last Reign; and if our Dissenters <hi>suffer'd</hi> so much <hi>then,</hi> as they <hi>now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain</hi> of, they know what they <hi>may suffer</hi> again, notwithstanding these <hi>Principles</hi> for Liberty of Conscience; for the <hi>same</hi> Principles obtain'd <hi>then,</hi> as do <hi>now.</hi> Upon the last withdrawing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Scotland,</hi> notwithstanding those <hi>Principles</hi> the poor <hi>Scotch</hi> felt the <hi>severity</hi> of those <hi>Penal Laws</hi> vvith a witness; and methinks it is not <hi>safe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting</hi> to such <hi>Principles</hi> as so often act by way of <hi>Antiperistasis,</hi> and produce Effects quite <hi>contrary</hi> to their own <hi>Natures:</hi> and however the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may indulge such Principles <hi>now</hi> they are <hi>convenient</hi> to serve a <hi>present turn,</hi> if the Scene ever alter, this <hi>private Conscience</hi> vvill be thought as great Heresie as a <hi>private Judgment;</hi> and whosoever now may ovvn it must then be guided by the <hi>publick Conscience</hi> of the Church, as well as by their <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are so many surprising Circumstances in this whole matter, as cannot but amaze a think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man: that so fierce a Zeal should be now kindled for a Liberty of <hi>Conscience,</hi> that a Liberty of <hi>Judgment</hi> will not be allowed, but vvho ever will not concurr in this Opinion must undergo the high displeasure; vvhereas there can be no <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> without <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And to be mortally angry with every man who is not of <hi>my Opinion,</hi> is no <hi>good Preface</hi> to granting every man a Liberty to <hi>think</hi> and <hi>act,</hi> as he pleases.</p>
            <p>If a Potentate should be so Zealous for Liberty of Conscience, as to <hi>change</hi> all his old <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> and <hi>Friendships,</hi> to receive his <hi>profess'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> into his bosom, and <hi>cast off</hi> his <hi>tried</hi> and <hi>experienced Friends;</hi> that he should forget all injuries and all kindnesses together, this would be such an effect of a great passion for Liberty of Conscience as was never known be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and vvhen Causes do not work naturally, vve suspect some preternatural ingredients mixed with them.</p>
            <p>That a Zeal <hi>against the Test</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> should be made a <hi>Test</hi> to the whole Nation; and that not vvithout severe Penalties too, <hi>viz.</hi> The forfeiture of our Princes favour, of all Places of Trust and Honour, and incapacity to serve in Parliaments if they can prevent it, or to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of any little Corporation.</p>
            <p>That for the sake of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> the whole Clergy must be <hi>forced</hi> to Publish the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, though they declare it to be <hi>against</hi> their <hi>Consciences:</hi> That the Archbishop and six of his Suffragans must be sent to the Tovver, for <hi>Petitioning</hi> for <hi>their own Liberty of Conscience;</hi> and whither they must have gone next God knows, unless they had been rescu'd by an <hi>honest Iury:</hi> That all those vvho did not Read the Declaration are still threatned with <hi>Suspensions,</hi> and <hi>Deprivations:</hi> Archdeacons and Chancellors commanded to turn <hi>Informers,</hi> though almost all of them must inform against <hi>themselves</hi> for not reading, or not sending the Declaration: and all this while the Laws are on <hi>their side.</hi> It is like to be a very <hi>terrible Liberty of Conscience,</hi> when it is grown up into the Maturity and strength of a <hi>Law,</hi> which like another <hi>Hercules</hi> can strangle all Laws and Liberties in its Cradle. These things make me apt to suspect that the best way to <hi>preserve Liberty of Conscience</hi> is to <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. For Thirdly, If there be any reason to suspect any <hi>other design</hi> than <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> as suppose to promote <hi>Popery,</hi> and by degrees to make it the <hi>Established Religion</hi> of the Nation, (which certainly is the Design, unless you can imagine, that Priests and Jesuits, and One who hath given up his Understanding and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them, can ever be <hi>without</hi> this Design,) You will easily be convinced that there is <hi>infinite hazzard</hi> in <hi>repealing</hi> the <hi>Test</hi> and the <hi>Penal Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> sets Papists upon an <hi>equal level</hi> with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and then the <hi>Favour</hi> of the Prince will set them <hi>above</hi> them: and when the whole <hi>power</hi> of the Nation, and the whole <hi>administration</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> is in Popish hands, there vvill <hi>need</hi> no Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws to persecute Protestants. If you say this is done in a great many instances now <hi>before</hi> such a <hi>Repeal;</hi> I answer, then You may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guess what will be done when those incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating Laws <hi>are repealed:</hi> And yet the Difference is very great; For while they are under such a <hi>legal Incapacity,</hi> the <hi>distrust</hi> of their power will make them more <hi>modest,</hi> which is the only thing that can plead their <hi>excuse</hi> hereafter; but when they have <hi>legal authority,</hi> they will shew their Nature without <hi>restraint.</hi> Men who have any thing to lose will act <hi>cautiously</hi> in prospect of an <hi>After-reckoning,</hi> or while these legal incapacities continue will be <hi>afraid</hi> to act; but when the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Authority and Power is in <hi>their</hi> hands. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Subjects will quickly find what a <hi>Popish Liberty of Conscience</hi> means.</p>
            <p>While these Laws continue, some <hi>professed</hi> Protestants vvhose Consciences are governed by their <hi>Interest</hi> are afraid to <hi>declare;</hi> and by these
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199742:3"/> means Popery wants hands and numbers to do its work: But when these Laws are removed, <hi>hopes of preferment</hi> will prevail on some, and <hi>fear</hi> on others; and vvhen this frozen Adder begins to grovv vvarm, and recover its <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>spirits,</hi> it will find its <hi>sting</hi> too.</p>
            <p>This would certainly overthrovv the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> vvhich is the most effectual vvay to let in <hi>Popery:</hi> For when all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacities are <hi>removed,</hi> Papists are as vvell quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for <hi>Church-Preferments</hi> as Protestants, and it vvill be an easie matter to find pretences, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the best Men to make vvay for them.</p>
            <p>We have four <hi>Catholick Bishops</hi> (as they vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call themselves) already prepared to fill vacant Sees; and if such Men have the impudence to publish their <hi>Pastoral Letter,</hi> and make their <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Visitations</hi> while all the Lavvs against them are in <hi>force,</hi> judge vvhat they will do vvhen they are repealed. Thus our Parishes may be filled vvith <hi>Roman Priests,</hi> and they indeed are the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test to serve under <hi>Roman Bishops.</hi> And if one <hi>Colledge</hi> be already seized into Popish hands, and the Protestant possessors turned out of their <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold;</hi> vvhen those Lavvs are Repealed, we may quickly see <hi>more</hi> follow them; and judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not a fair and easie step to Popery.</p>
            <p>Nay, I have heard some good Lavvyers say, That vvhen the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> are <hi>repealed,</hi> Popery is the <hi>Established Religion</hi> of the Nation: That vvhen a <hi>repealing Law</hi> is repealed, the <hi>repealed Law</hi> revives: I am not so good a Lawyer as to judge of this, but I think it is vvorth your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidering.</p>
            <p>But who knows, vvhen all the Ecclesiastical Laws are Repealed, vvhat the Kings Supremacy and his Ecclesiastical Commission may do? There have been great and big vvords said of it of late; and I believe You had better keep your <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> than fall under the lash of a <hi>Popish Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I knovv there hath been a great talk of an <hi>Equivalent,</hi> but I vvould gladly know vvhat that <hi>Equivalent</hi> should be. Shall it incapacitate all Papists for any Office either in Church or State? That must not be, for fear of depriving the King of the <hi>natural right</hi> he has to the service of his Subjects; and then I am sure there can be <hi>no Equivalent</hi> for the repeal of the incapacitating Laws.</p>
            <p>But you say there shall be a <hi>New Charter</hi> for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> the <hi>Protestant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conscience.</hi> Now shall this be <hi>with</hi> a Penalty or <hi>without</hi> one? If <hi>with</hi> a penalty, then you do not <hi>repeal,</hi> but only <hi>exchange</hi> your Penal Laws; and if Penal Laws are not such Unchristian things, but they may be allowed, we <hi>cannot</hi> have <hi>better</hi> for the security of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than we have; and therefore vve had best <hi>keep these.</hi> Is there any other fault in our <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> (especially when they are <hi>not executed</hi>) but that they are too great a security to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Protestant Inte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est?</hi> And if this be a reason for Protestants at <hi>this time</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal them, I have done. But if this <hi>new</hi> Estab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishment be <hi>without</hi> a penalty, what is it good for?</p>
            <p>When these Penal Lavvs are removed, Papists are qualified to sit in both Houses of Parliament: and vvho knows vvhether <hi>Closetting</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> of <hi>Corporations,</hi> and such other Arts may not quickly make a Popish Parliament? And then Good Night to Your <hi>New Establishment</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conscience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These things I hope Sir, You will consider in your Choice of Members for Parliament; and not be cheated vvith the Popular cry of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> into the <hi>vilest</hi> and <hi>most despicable Slavery</hi> both of Soul and Body.</p>
            <closer>I am <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your very Cordial Friend, and faithful Monitor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Tot de Hague, gedruckt door Hans Verdraeght, 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>